<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brent F. Sanderson</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Brent F. Sanderson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 12:59:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Rachel Teubner on Loss</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/rachel-teubner-on-loss/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 12:39:04 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/rachel-teubner-on-loss/</guid>
        <description>Brent F. Sanderson //localhost:1313/posts/rachel-teubner-on-loss/ -&lt;p&gt;This morning, &lt;a href=&#34;https://hedgehogreview.com/web-features/thr/posts/losing-a-personal-history&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Hedgehog Review&lt;/em&gt; posted a moving and very insightful piece by Rachel Teubner exploring her sense of loss and the hardship and misunderstanding of having a miscarriage.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;My grief felt eccentric, if not unique: The whole world was trying to organize a response to a pandemic, and all I could think about was that little bundle of potential that had died. I loved the idea of that baby and everything that, for a little over two weeks, I had been able to imagine would follow.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I tried to pray for understanding. Sometimes I prayed for Elijah. I had read &lt;em&gt;A Severe Mercy&lt;/em&gt; over the summer, a book I thought might help me figure out what to do, how to think about bereavement. The writer Sheldon Vanauken had lost his brilliant, beautiful young wife; was it wrong that I felt my loss equivalent to his?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I read something by the food writer Nina Planck about planting bulbs after a miscarriage as a kind of poetic mourning ritual. In October we carved three jack-o-lanterns: one for Ella, one for Isaiah, one for Elijah Nowell. When we turned on the battery powered tea lights at night, it felt like a prayer, the least I could do to reassure this baby that we hadn’t forgotten him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the father of four wonderful children. We would have had a fifth, a little girl whom we never got to name, but my wife suffered a miscarriage. This piece by Teubner has helped me understand my own grief over that baby who was never born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not you or your family have ever gone through a miscarriage, I strongly recommend you read this remarkable essay.&lt;/p&gt;
- //localhost:1313/posts/rachel-teubner-on-loss/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Advice for Edtech Startups</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/advice-for-edtech-startups/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 18:29:54 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/advice-for-edtech-startups/</guid>
        <description>Brent F. Sanderson //localhost:1313/posts/advice-for-edtech-startups/ -&lt;p&gt;Below are some scattered thoughts offered to all education technology startup looking to sell a new product into K-12 schools. They come after a decade in the trenches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many districts&amp;rsquo; content filtering software has a blanket ban on all .io domains. Don&amp;rsquo;t give your web app a .io address unless you want to spend a ton of time helping confused teachers apply for a whitelisting exception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Districts will care about your student data privacy policies. You will be asked if you are compliant with FERPA and COPPA. Do you know what those are? Are you compliant?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many districts have a policy that students cannot use any application that involves signing in with a username and password. How will you grant those students access?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your web application make use of the browser&amp;rsquo;s local storage like IndexedDB or the Cache API? Many managed Chromebook policies used by schools either prevent local storage altogether or clear the cache at regular intervals. If that breaks your app, you need to find a solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many schools&amp;rsquo; content filtering blocks common CDN platforms. If you use a CDN to serve static assets as part of your application, make sure you to include the CDN&amp;rsquo;s URL as part of your list of domains that need to be white-listed by IT staff. It&amp;rsquo;s very possible you&amp;rsquo;re serving assets from multiple subdomains, so be sure to include each one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to launch a product and most schools or districts don&amp;rsquo;t have a line-item in their budget to buy that product, you should strongly re-think trying to launch that product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- //localhost:1313/posts/advice-for-edtech-startups/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>The Flipped Classroom in the Age of AI</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/the-flipped-classroom-in-the-age-of-ai/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:15:25 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/the-flipped-classroom-in-the-age-of-ai/</guid>
        <description>Brent F. Sanderson //localhost:1313/posts/the-flipped-classroom-in-the-age-of-ai/ -&lt;p&gt;During a decade spent teaching high school coding and computer science, I have almost exclusively taught while using the flipped classroom model. I strongly believe that this model is the best way to teach young people how to write code, and when free access to LLM chatbots has upended education (it is common to hear disheartened teachers throw out the phrase &amp;ldquo;homework apocalypse&amp;rdquo;), I think that for the disciplines that can manage it, the flipped classroom will become a necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the nitty gritty, I should first answer the question, &amp;ldquo;what is a flipped classroom?&amp;rdquo; as I know that even many other teachers are unfamiliar with this teaching strategy. The flipped classroom model inverts the kinds of activities that are traditionally given as classwork and homework. In a traditional high school classroom, a teacher might lecture for the majority of class time, then assign students a set of problems to do for homework. Class time is dedicated to conveying information, and homework is used to get students practicing. In the flipped classroom model, students would be reading a textbook chapter or watching a lecture video on their own time before coming to class, and then working through associated problems during class time. They do the bulk of their practice in the presence of their teacher, and homework is focused on the dissemination of whatever information is needed to succeed with classwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name &amp;ldquo;flipped classroom model&amp;rdquo; was coined in 2007 by Jonathan Bergman and Aaron Sams; though undoubtedly fantastic, innovative teachers, they were not the first to use this model. I first encountered a flipped classroom as a computer science student at Belmont University, where professors Bill Hooper and Joyce Crowell used the model extensively in their introductory programming courses (and I&amp;rsquo;m very sure they&amp;rsquo;d never heard of Bergman or Sams). In fact, teachers had been using the same or similar instructional strategies for decades before the model was codified under the name &amp;ldquo;flipped classroom.&amp;rdquo; You can read more about the history of the instructional style here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1349598.pdf&#34; title=&#34;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1349598.pdf&#34;&gt;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1349598.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, flipped classrooms are often classified as a kind of &amp;ldquo;blended learning,&amp;rdquo; with the assumption that teachers will record lecture videos and post them into a learning management system. This approach to a flipped classroom can obviously be very effective (and also involve a lot of up-front work by the teacher), but there&amp;rsquo;s no strict necessity to involve technology at all. You could just as easily use a text book and assign students to &amp;ldquo;do the reading,&amp;rdquo; before they come to class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For teaching students how to write code, the flipped classroom is to my mind the best approach. As anyone who has ever learned to program a computer knows, writing code is a skill. As computer science teachers, our goal is not to fill our students brains full of information. Our goal is to teach our students a skill. Therefore, it seems obvious to me that we should spend the majority of the time we have with students working with them on skills development, and not information relay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they first begin, learning to write code can be very difficult for students, if only because it tends to be so different from anything they have done in other courses. Whenever I&amp;rsquo;ve taught an intro class full of students who have never done any programming before, there is always a distinct period of time at the beginning of the year when the whole class feels like they&amp;rsquo;re in over their heads, but invariably, a moment occurs for almost every student when something clicks and the unique mode of thinking inherent to writing code starts to feel natural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This moment occurs at a different time for each student: for some, it&amp;rsquo;s at the end of first week, others after a couple months, and some towards the end of year. Because there is always great disparities for when each student has this breakthrough, it&amp;rsquo;s critical to be present as a teacher during practicing and skills development to give each student individualized support. This level of support is only possible if you&amp;rsquo;re not spending 45 minutes or more lecturing. In a flipped classroom setting that&amp;rsquo;s done well, the majority of instruction will be given one-on-one or to small groups while the rest of the class is busy with their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found other reasons for teaching this way. The bulk of my teaching career was spent in schools where I could not guarantee that students would have access to a computer, access to the internet, or even dedicated time to do work (many of my students worked full time jobs after they left school in the afternoon). It&amp;rsquo;s easy to take for granted that every student has the ability to go home and work on a computer after school without realizing that the assumption is one of economic privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left a career in software to become a high school teacher in the 2010s. Since starting a couple big wrecking balls hit the world of education: namely, the COVID-19 pandemic and the widespread proliferation of free LLM-powered chatbots. Some approaches to teaching no longer work, but certain old approaches may be the tools that we need to make sure learning and skills-development still happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One huge, glaring, obvious, and much-lamented drawback to the vast majority of students having instantaneous, free access to ChatGPT (or Gemini, or Claude, or DeepSeek, &amp;amp;c &amp;amp;c) is that if (almost) every student has the option to never do homework again, (almost) no students will ever do homework again. When homework&amp;rsquo;s main purpose is to enforce the development of skills, the AI cheating epidemic is devastating to all the wider goals of education. However, if homework&amp;rsquo;s focus is on knowledge conveyance, things start to look less devastating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what camp into which you as a reader may fall in the debates about AI&amp;rsquo;s role in education (AI will save our education system; AI will destroy whatever&amp;rsquo;s left of our education system; within clear limits, students should learn how to use LLM technologies; something else), it seems obvious to me that using an LLM chatbot for knowledge consumption is much less deleterious to learning outcomes than using it to write a paper for you or to complete a coding assignment. To some extent, if I told a student to read a textbook chapter about for loops before class, and they used ChatGPT to read a summary instead, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t care. As long as it adequately prepared them to do our in-class assignment the next day, they&amp;rsquo;ve accomplished what I&amp;rsquo;ve asked. I&amp;rsquo;d care a lot more if I asked them to write 10 for loops for homework and they had a chatbot do it for them. Now they&amp;rsquo;re no longer developing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every English teacher reading this post is certainly muttering to themselves right now, reading is, of course, itself a skill. It&amp;rsquo;s not so easy as I&amp;rsquo;ve made it sound to shunt all types of assignments neatly into two binary camps of &amp;ldquo;knowledge conveyance&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;skills development,&amp;rdquo; which is why the flipped classroom doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for every course or every discipline. English courses may be hit the hardest by the rise of LLMs, and it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that one of the best strategies to protect students from their worst instincts isn&amp;rsquo;t very helpful for English teachers in the trenches, fighting the good fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, for so many classes, the flipped classroom is undoubtedly the right answer. For many disciplines, including coding, most CTE courses, many math classes, and any course that emphasizes project-based or inquiry-driven learning, teaching with a flipped classroom is probably better for student learning regardless of any home apocalypses that might be at hand. Even if the rise of LLM chatbots proves to be largely a disaster for our education system, perhaps a widespread move to counteract cheating by adopting flipped classrooms will lead to student gains among those who are willing to try something new.&lt;/p&gt;
- //localhost:1313/posts/the-flipped-classroom-in-the-age-of-ai/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Scaffolding Computer Science Curriculum</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/what-makes-for-good-k12-computer-science-curriculum/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 11:03:51 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/what-makes-for-good-k12-computer-science-curriculum/</guid>
        <description>Brent F. Sanderson //localhost:1313/posts/what-makes-for-good-k12-computer-science-curriculum/ -&lt;p&gt;As a seasoned computer science teacher and curriculum manager, I believe that all strong computer science curricula have appropriate scaffolding, are project-based, and are easily and effectively differentiable. I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing a series of posts on each of these attributes, but today, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do a deep dive into scaffolding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written a lot of CS curriculum. Hundreds of hours worth (perhaps thousands), for my classroom, for my own company and for other companies that valued my expertise. As a high school teacher, I&amp;rsquo;ve also used countless other curricula, some very effective, and many fair to terrible. Because I&amp;rsquo;ve had first-hand experience with so many curriculum products, I know that a poorly scaffolded curriculum is detrimental to student outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the right scaffolds in place, students won&amp;rsquo;t develop independent thinking, and may give up entirely before they&amp;rsquo;ve started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-scaffolding&#34;&gt;What is scaffolding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not an educator, this word probably makes you think of the temporary support structures used by construction workers to reach tall places. On the other hand, if you’re a teacher, your primary association may be something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the education world, “scaffolding” has a specific technical meaning. It refers to the way that a teacher or curriculum slowly removes instructional supports as students learn. The goal of scaffolding is to guide students to independent thinking and problem solving. We want students to learn how to approach a wide range of problems, not just the specific task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaffolding is important for learners in every field, but it’s particularly relevant when teaching computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most K-12 learners have little experience writing code, so they’ll need extra support up front. Writing code is a skill. Computer science learners are not just memorizing facts or syntax. They’re learning a new way to think. If we want them to master skills, we must guide them towards independent thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;scaffolding-for-cs&#34;&gt;Scaffolding for CS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what does scaffolding look like in a computer science curriculum?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of a project, you’ll want to be very explicit in telling students what code to write and where. If a student has never written an if statement or a for loop, you can’t expect them to understand how to do it just by hearing the theory behind it and seeing a syntax example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a project goes on, students should receive less support. Each step should require a little bit more independent thought. Students build on what they’ve learned, slowly learning not just a programming language, but how to use code to solve a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we’re teaching them not just the “what” of programming, but also “why” and “how.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you know if a curriculum isn’t scaffolded enough?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unscaffolded computer science curriculum falls into one of two extremes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first extreme gives too little support to students&lt;/strong&gt;. It provides abstract information and then asks students to perform a concrete task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example assignment might show students the documentation for the Java class &lt;em&gt;String&lt;/em&gt;, and then ask them, “find and use methods in this documentation to write a new method that states whether a given input &lt;em&gt;String&lt;/em&gt; is a palindrome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This assignment leapfrogs several levels of thinking, asking students to synthesize lecture material without ever getting them to analyze or apply. It doesn’t even check for comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The second extreme gives too much support.&lt;/strong&gt; It will give students project to work on, but will spell out what to do for every step along the way, like a recipe. An example assignment that gives too much support might be a video tutorial called “How to Build Space Invaders in Python with PyGame,” that never pulls back and asks a student to figure out the next step themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students will end the assignment with a finished product, but they won’t ever be required to solve a problem. They’ll be told exactly what code to write the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Both extremes cater to the students who don’t need a teacher.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An exceptionally self-directed student given too little support will find a way to solve the problem. This will probably involve doing research and practice outside of the curriculum to gain the support lacking in the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An exceptionally self-directed student given too much support will think outside the task at hand to learn why the project steps work. This will probably involve experimenting and adding new features not requested by the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the students who need a teacher never really learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t give your students enough support, they’ll have nothing to show for their frustration, and probably won’t want to keep learning to write code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you give your students too much support, they’ll never learn to write code beyond following a set of steps. Students will never get to be creative, and they won’t feel like they know what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-do-it-right&#34;&gt;How to do it right&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does a properly scaffolded computer science curriculum look like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said in the introduction, I&amp;rsquo;ve written countless computer science curricula. Many different courses, for a variety of companies. Sometimes I had the freedom to craft a curriculum&amp;rsquo;s direction myself, other times I had to follow the style and goals of a different curriculum manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I was designing the whole curriculum myself, I used the following structure for every lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, students read about a new code concept or structure. They’ll learn a big idea and some syntax. The concept might be something like arrays, class inheritance, or Boolean operators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, students watch a short video showing someone write code using the new concept. They get to see the skill applied, along with an explanation for how and why it was written that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the short text and video lessons, students start working on a project that uses the concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the real student learning happened in part three. Delivering new content with text or a video is necessary, just like lectures are necessary, but all good teachers know that watching videos or listening to a lecture is one of the worst ways to learn. Students don&amp;rsquo;t internalize knowledge or develop new skill until and unless they&amp;rsquo;ve done hands-on work. Similarly, all good curriculum writers know that hands-on work is where you have to scaffold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we don&amp;rsquo;t have enough scaffolding, students stare at a blank screen forever (or immediately use their favorite AI tools to get the correct answers without ever truly engaging with the problem). Too much scaffolding, and all you&amp;rsquo;re really testing is your students ability to copy and paste from a set of project instructions (granted, that can be a useful skill in its own right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To properly scaffold project instructions, the first few steps should start by telling students exactly what to do. &amp;ldquo;Open this file. Find this code section. Go make this exact code change in line 5.&amp;rdquo; As students work, each step should offer a bit less direction. Next, students will be applying the same idea in different place. As the steps progress, they&amp;rsquo;ll be told less and less what to do, applying the main idea in new ways. Eventually, the instructions will have them adding new features without explicit direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, several years ago I authored a project called &amp;ldquo;Rock Dodger&amp;rdquo; that was embedded in a year-long Java curriculum for high schoolers. The cored idea was teaching students when and how to use getter and setter methods to enable interaction between objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/ptWuyxJ-mLff4Hnf.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first steps showed students exactly what to do, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/step2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple steps later, the training wheels started to come off just a little bit:
&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/step4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they work, the project instructions direct students to look at former steps to figure out how to perform new, similar tasks:
&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/nine.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;
Until finally, we expect the students to think critically about how to proceed forward on their own:
&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/ten.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;
Because of how the project is scaffolded, students are slowly taught how to reason through each step and guided towards creative, independent thinking. Building a computer science curriculum this way doesn&amp;rsquo;t just build knowledge, it builds skills. A well-scaffolded curriculum also supports students and teacher of all levels and backgrounds, not just those with the highest aptitude or outside experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That ends my ruminations on the importance of scaffolding in computer science curriculum. In a week or two, I&amp;rsquo;ll post some writings on the importance of project-driven curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
- //localhost:1313/posts/what-makes-for-good-k12-computer-science-curriculum/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Statement of Purpose</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/posts/statement-of-purpose/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 10:54:59 -0600</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/statement-of-purpose/</guid>
        <description>Brent F. Sanderson //localhost:1313/posts/statement-of-purpose/ -&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started a new personal website, as of December 1, 2025, as a place for me to post publicly some of my thoughts and writings. I will write about whatever strikes me, though common themes are likely to include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arts and Literature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a natural procrastinator, I am also publicly setting a deadline for myself that the first substantial piece of writing will appear here by Monday, December 8, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
- //localhost:1313/posts/statement-of-purpose/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 